<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A helpe to the right understanding of a discourse concerning independency. Lately published by William Pryn of Lincolnes Inne, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W683B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E259_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871086</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871086</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97099)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 44:E259[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A helpe to the right understanding of a discourse concerning independency. Lately published by William Pryn of Lincolnes Inne, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno Dom. 1644. [i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Walwyn by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1644 only; Thomason catalogue lists under 1645; McMichael and Taft, The writings of William Walwyn, p.131, give 1644/5.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 6th London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Independency examined, unmasked, refuted.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159262:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Helpe to the right underſtanding of a DISCOURSE CONCERNING INDEPENDENCY. Lately publiſhed by <hi>WILLIAM PRYN</hi> OF <hi>Lincolnes Inne,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 12.13.</hi>
               </bibl> The evill man is ſnared by the wickedneſſe of his lips, but the juſt man ſhall come out of adverſity.</q>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:159262:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159262:2"/>
            <head>A helpe to the right underſtanding of a Diſcourſe concerning INDEPENDENCY, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AS it is a very great benefit to the world when wiſe and conſiderate men, ſuffer for maintenance of a juſt cauſe: ſo alſo it proveth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times very prejudiciall to a Nation, when raſh inconſiderate men, wiſe only in their owne ſtrong conceits, doe ſuffer, though for a cauſe as juſt as common freedome it ſelfe: becauſe ſuffering winneth reputation to the perſon that ſuffereth, whereby his ſayings, opinions, and writings carry authority with them: and though never ſo much blended with ſlightneſſe, arrogance, impurity, violence, error, and want of charity: yet make they deep impreſſion in the minds of many well meaning people, and ſway them to the like, or diſlike of things: not as they are really good, or palpably evill in themſelves, but according to the gloſſe, or dirt, that ſuch men through ignorance, impatience, or malice caſt upon them.</p>
            <p>For inſtance whereof, I am ſomewhat troubled that I muſt alledge Mr. <hi>William Pryn,</hi> who to his great commendation in the late arbitrary times ſuffered for the maintenance of the juſt liberties of his Country: but in a great example of late it is too ſadly proved that he that did the greateſt ſervice, may live to doe the greateſt miſchiefe: and I am fully inſtructed. That only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in well-doing, is praiſe-worthy: and therefore I conceive I may without breach of charity, be as bold with him as with any other man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: that others may learne by me to reſpect good men no longer then they continue ſo.</p>
            <p>Of late he is fallen upon ſo unhappy a ſubject (The difference of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters of Religion) and hath ſo totally engaged himſelfe therein, that even men who have formerly had him in great repute for integrity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to doubt his ends; ſuppoſing that he ſtrikes in with the riſing party in hope to raiſe himſelfe with them, and by them; and that he is carried away with that infirmity unto which men of his tribe have been much ſubject.</p>
            <p>Others there are that conceive he is defective only in his underſtanding, and eaſily out-witted, and wrought to doe that, which he intended not to do, charitably hoping by his endeavours in the argument of Church government, that he really intended the reconciling of all parties, and that he hath unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily wrought a contrary effect, and made the diviſion greater, through his want of judgement, and naturally paſſionate weakneſſe: inconſiderately engaging, and (being engaged) and proſecuting with violence: and they argue it to be ſo, from his publiſhing Romes maſter-piece; and the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops Diary; intending, no doubt, to blazon the vileneſſe of that Arch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary to the world; whereas to an adviſed Reader, it will be evident, that the firſt is framed of purpoſe to lay the deſigne of all our troubles upon the Papiſts; and make the Archbiſhop ſuch an enemy thereunto, as that they plotted to take away his life; as if Satan were divided againſt Satan; and his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159262:3"/>Diary is ſo ſubtilly contrived, as that among thoſe from whom he expecteth honour, it cannot faile to worke moſt powerfully thereunto, ſo great are his good workes therein expreſſed, ſo large are his pious intentions, ſo watchfull over his wayes, ſo ſeldome offending, ſo penitent after offences, ſo devout in prayer, ſo learned and patheticall in his expreſſions; that to any that are but tainted with the leaſt Prelaticall ſuperſtition, he will appeare a Saint, if not equall to <hi>Noah, Lot</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> yet full parallel with the moſt holy Primitive Fathers; eſpecially when they ſhall conſider that theſe his works were publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by his greateſt enemy, which was the Archbiſhops Maſter-piece indeed, being both written of purpoſe to be publiſhed in their beſt ſeaſon; and by a perſon that ſhould moſt advantage the deceit: if it had not been ſo, they had eaſily been fiend or concealed, paſt his finding: no man can thinke the Biſhop ſo impolitick, as after ſo long impriſonment, not to be warned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his notes.</p>
            <p>Others judge him to be much of the Archbiſhops ſpirit, his late adverſary, and feare that if he had equall power to that he once had, he would exceed him in cruelty of perſecution; and their reaſon is, becauſe he is ſo violently buſie already, egging and inciting the Parliament, like their evill Genius, to acts of tyranny againſt a people he knows innocent: how much more would he rage againſt them had he that command of cenſure, fine, pillory, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment and baniſhment, which the Archbiſhop unjuſtly uſurped; eſpecially ſince his rage againſt them has ſo exceeded all bounds of modeſty already, as to affirme that their writings are <hi>deſtructive to the very being of Parliaments, and as bad or worſe then the Popiſh Gunpowder-plot,</hi> and to tearme their honeſt and ſubmiſſe demeanours, <hi>Inſolencies, unparalleld publicke violations and impeachments of the rights and priviledges of Parliament, and of the tranquility and ſafety of our Church and State.</hi> I am at ſtand Methinks, and cannot but grieve within my ſelfe to conſider how full ſwolne with bitter malice, yea and the very poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Aſpes, that breaſt muſt needs be from whence proceeds ſuch malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſcandalous ſpeeches, yet ſo groſſely untrue and unſutable to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Independents.</p>
            <p>Men likewiſe ſay that this muſt needs proceed from ſpleene: for if he were a really conſcientious man he would firſt pull the beame out of his own eye, as he is a Lawyer, and examine his owne wayes in the courſe of his practiſe, or ſet out ſomething to ſet out the unlawfulneſſe of tythes, as learned Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> hath done. Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> profeſſeth the true Chriſtian Religion, and that moſt zealouſly, yet continueth to take fees for pleading mens cauſes, a thing that the vertuous men amongſt the very heathens accounted baſe, and would doe it gratis: and what fees taketh he? no leſſe then treble the value of what is taken by pleaders in Popiſh Countries; but he taketh as little as any man of his calling, and no more but what is lawfull for him to take: therein, ſay they, conſiſts the miſery of the Common-wealth, with all other the extreame abuſes of our Laws, the very way of the ending of controverſies, being ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally pernicious and full of vexation: that were he truly conſcientious for the good of the whole Nation, as he pretendeth, he would have laid open to the Parliament, how improper it is that our Laws ſhould be writen in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159262:3"/>language, that a plaine man cannot underſtand ſo much as a Writ without the helpe of Councell; how prejudiciall it is that for ending a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toverſie, men muſt travell Terme after Terme from all quarters of the Land to London, tiring their perſons and ſpirits, waſting their eſtates, and beggering their families; tending to nothing but the vexation of the people, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching of Lawyers; with a little labour had he been ſo vertuouſly diſpoſed, he could have diſcovered the corrupt originall thereof, and have layed open all the abſurdities therein, and ſhewed the diſagreement thereof to the rules of Chriſtianity: he could alſo have ſhewed to the Parliament what of our Lawes themſelves are unneceſſary, what are prejudiciall to good men, and have moved for reducing all to an agreement with Chriſtianity: were he (ſay they) truly pious, and could deny himſelfe, this he would have done, though he had thereby made himſelfe equall to men of low degree, both in eſtate, food, and rayment: yea though for his livelihood hee had beene conſtrained to have laboured with his hands, &amp;c. This indeed had beene a proper worke for him a Chriſtian Lawyer in a time of Reformation: What needed he to have meddled againſt the Independent and Separation, there being ſo many learned Divines (as hee himſelfe eſteemes them) ſitting in Councell ſo neare the Parliament, which ſhewes him to bee too officious?</p>
            <p>And as concerning Church-Government: If hee had really inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the good of the Nation, and the weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all peaceable minded men, he would have had in minde ſuch conſiderations as theſe.</p>
            <p>The Parliament are now upon ſetling the affaires of the Church, a thing of a very nice and dainty nature, eſpecially being undertaken in a time of a homebred Warre: If it be not very adviſedly and cautiouſly done, it may ſoone divide the wel-affected party within it ſelfe, then which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more pernitious and deſtructive: already I have ſeene ſome that have laid downe Armes, and many withdraw their perſons and eſtates into forreigne parts, for no other cauſe but for being diſturbed or diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in exerciſing of their conſciences in matters of Religion: And it was but thus in the Prelaticall time. I finde by my ſelfe, that Chriſtians cannot live, though they ſhould enjoy all naturall freedome and content, where they are not free to worſhip God in a way of Religion: And I finde alſo by my ſelfe that Chriſtians cannot worſhip God in any way but what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with their underſtandings and conſciences; and although I may be at liberty to worſhip God according to that way which the Parliament ſhall ſet up for a generall rule to the whole Nation; yet if I were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that I might lawfully ſubmit thereunto, all the torments in the World ſhould not enforce mee: and this I finde to bee the caſe of many conſcientious people, very well affected to the Parliament and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon freedome: Men that have ſpent their eſtates, and hazarded their lives as freely in defence of juſt Government, as any men whatſoever; and whether they are under the names of Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, Separation, Independents, or Antinomies; wee have had all their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159262:4"/>moſt affectionate helpe in throwing down Epiſcopacy and arbitrary govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: men they are that ſtill remaine in moſt oppoſition to the Popiſh and malignant parties; ſomewhat we muſt doe for the eaſe of theſe our brethren, it muſt not be in the ſettlement of our Reformation that they remaine under the ſame reſtraint or moleſtation for their conſciences as they were in the Prelaticall time; we muſt doe as we would be done unto: if any ſort of them were greater in number then we, and had authority to countenance them, we ſhould eſteem it hard meaſure, to be reſtrained from exerciſing our Religion according to our conſciences, or to be compelled by fines, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, or other puniſhments, to worſhip contrary to our conſciences, we muſt beare with one anothers infirmities; no condition of men in our dayes have an infallibility of judgement: every one ought to be fully perſwaded in his owne minde of the lawfulneſſe of the way wherein he ſerveth God; if one man obſerve a day to the Lord, and others not; and both out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God, both are allowed by the Apoſtle; and the one is not to moleſt, no not to deſpiſe or condemne. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 3. much leſſe compell the other to his judgement, becauſe whatſoever is not of faith or full aſſurance of minde is ſin: had Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> debated thus with himſelfe, he had ſhewed himſelfe a true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Chriſt and his Apoſtle: differing opinions would not then have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſuch abominable, damnable things in his ſight: The dealing of our Saviour with thoſe moſt erronious Sadduces, would have come into his mind, they beleeved that there was neither Angell nor Spirit, and that there was no reſurrection: Opinions as contrary to the current of the then Interpreters, as any in our time, and yet they profeſſed it openly, as appeareth by their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting our Saviour, and were as unreproved of him as of authority; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves their queſtion by an anſwer which removed that abſurdity which they thought impoſſible: briefly telling them, That they neither marry nor are married, but as the Angels of God in heaven; uſing them gently, without threats or reproaches.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> had thought of this Subject, with ſuch like conſiderations, he would ſoone have ſeen, <hi>That the people of a Nation in chuſing of a Parliament cannot confer more then that power which was juſtly in themſelves: the plain rule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this: That which a man may not voluntarily binde himſelfe to doe, or to forbear to doe, without ſinne: That he cannot entruſt or refer unto the ordering of any other: Whatſoever (be it Parliament, Generall Councels, or Nationall Aſſemblies:) But all things concerning the worſhip and ſervice of God, and of that nature; that a man cannot without wilfull ſin, either binde himſelfe to doe any thing therein contrary to his underſtanding and conſcience: nor to forbeare to doe that which his underſtanding and conſcience bindes him to performe: therefore no man can refer matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any others regulation. And what cannot be giuen, cannot be received: and then as a particular man cannot be robbed of that which he never had; ſo neither can a Parliament, or any other juſt Authority be violated in, or deprived of a power which cannot be entruſted unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Emperours, and Kings, and Popes, have aſſumed an abſolute power over Nations in matters of Religion, need not to have beene ſo laboriouſly proved; nor that Councels and Parliaments have done the like: the matter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159262:4"/>is what they have done of right: who knowes not that all theſe have erred as often as they did ſo: our preſent Parliament have greater light then any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and propoſe to themſelves to abandon what ever former Parliaments have either aſſumed, or done upon miſ-information; and have not yet decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to diſſent from the fore recited rule: and then Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> may conſider, whether he hath not extreamly miſpent his time, and with much uncharitableneſſe injured that faithfull ſervant of God, and ſincere lover of his Country, Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> a man that to my knowledge, and to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many, values neither life nor livelihood, could he therewith, or with loſſe thereof, purchaſe a peaceable liberty to his Country, or a juſt Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary government; ſo far is he, or that other worthy man Mr. <hi>Burton;</hi> or any Independent, Anabaptiſt, Browniſt, or any of the Separation now extant, from deſerving either thoſe ſlight, but arrogant expreſſions of his in his ſaid Epiſtle, telling the honourable Parliament, That he knows not what evill Genius, and Pithagorian Metempſychoſis, the Antiparliamentary ſoules for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly dwelling in our defunct Prelats earthly Tabernacles, are tranſmigrated into, and revived into a new generation of men (ſtarted up of late amongſt us) commonly knowne by the name of Independents: ſuch bumbaſt inck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne tearmes, ſavouring ſo much of a meer pedanticke, as ill beſeemeth his relation to that ſupream power of Parliament: And thogh thoſe Independents, for the moſt part are ſuch by his owne acknowledgement, whoſe affections and actions have demonſtrated them to be reall and cordiall to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Church of England, for which (ſaith he) and for their piety they are to be highly honoured, yet hath not he ſo much charity as to ſhew any inclination that they ſhould be relieved in their juſt deſire of Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but proſecutes all thoſe their ſeverall judgements, as derogatory and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive unto Parliament and Church in their Anarchicall and Antiparlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary poſitions; for which, and for their late gathering of Independent Churches, contrary to Parliamentary injunctions (which were never ſeen) they are he ſayes, to be juſtly blamed as great Diſturbers of our publicke peace and unity: theſe his great words make a great noiſe, I confeſſe: a man that did not converſe amongſt theſe people, may eaſily be induced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them to be very dangerous. Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> is of great credit with many in authority, and how far he hath therein done them wrong, his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will one day tell him to his coſt.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> were a ſtranger to the Separation, and unacquainted with the innocency of their wayes and intentions, I might charitably judge him to plead for the perſecution of Gods people ignorantly, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did: but ſince he cannot but know that they are both in affection and action re all and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall to the Parliament, as himſelfe confeſſes, and hath found them for his owne particular compaſſionate in his ſufferings, and liberally aſſiſtant to him in his miſeries: I profeſſe, I can make no other conſtruction of his ſo violent pleading for perſecution, and incenſing the Parliament againſt a People he knowes harmleſſe, and modeſt and reaſonable in their deſires whoſe utmoſt end is only not to be moleſted in their ſerving of God: I can make no other conſtruction of it, I ſay, that engagement to the Divines, and ſome intereſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159262:5"/>of his owne hath begot a hardneſſe over his heart, and clouded that noble courage, and common ſpirit which did poſſeſſe him. If he wanted informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I would labour with him, but ſince I cannot doubt but that he hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of that, I will leave him till the truth and excellency of that freedome againſt which he fights, till the ſincerity and uprightneſſe of the Separation which he delivers up to the ſword, in theſe words, <hi>Immedicabile vulnus enſe recidendum eſt,</hi> make him one day appeare even to his preſent admirers, the man he is indeed.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, I turne to the people, and deſire them to enquire after the Separation, and have full knowledge of them: they will then finde they are extreamly miſunderſtood by authority, and all others that apprehend them to be any other then a quiet harmleſſe people, no way dangerous or troubleſome to humane ſociety: I have found them to be an ingenious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring people, and charitable both in their cenſures of others, and due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the poore. I am become their advocate, out of no engagement or relation to them, I profeſſe, more then what my knowledge of their ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and true affection to their Country hath begotten in me.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> I need not ſpeak much of, he is a man ſo well knowne, that Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> ſo rigid urging of his expreſſions upon him, as he hath too largely and ſpleeniſhly done in his Epiſtle, making ſo unſavoury and utterly diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned compariſons betwixt him, and the malignant Prelats, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parliamentary Cavaliers, that a man that knows the antipathy betweene them cannot but ſtand amazed thereat; and neceſſarily conclude that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath blinded not only the light of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> conſcience, but of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding alſo, and then after a moſt unchriſtian application, his ſentence is in theſe diſmall old Antichriſtian and Prelaticall tearms; if they will not be reclaimed, <hi>fiat juſtitia,</hi> better ſome ſhould ſuffer then all periſh: but happy it is, that <hi>the power of Parliament is not in</hi> Mr. <hi>Pryn:</hi> if it were (in the minde he is now in) 'tis much to be doubted, his part would differ little from <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> or <hi>Gardiners</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes: but bleſſed be God, it is otherwiſe; nor will that juſt Authority I preſume be moved either with his fierce excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, or incomparable flatteries to doe any thing contrary to right reaſon and true Chriſtianity: nor is there indeed (the fore mentioned rule holding) any cauſe why that ſupreme Authority ſhould be offended: for all ſorts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, whether Anabaptiſts or Browniſts, or Antinomians, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe all agree, that in all Civill and Military cauſes and affaires, they have an abſolute ſupreme power: And if they ſhall conceive it juſt and neceſſary for the State to propoſe one way of worſhip for a generall rule throughout the Land, and ſhall ingratiate the ſame by an exemption from all offence and ſcandall of weake conſciences as far as is poſſible; The Independents, &amp;c. have nothing to oppoſe againſt their wiſdomes: and if the publicke way ſhould be ſuch as ſhould agree with any of their judgements and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they would moſt readily joyne in fellowſhip therein: but if their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and conſciences ſhould not be fully ſatisfied concerning the ſame, then whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne; and they cannot but disjoyne: and in ſuch a caſe, all good men that know them will ſhew themſelves true Chriſtians
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159262:5"/>indeed, in becomming humble ſuters to the Parliament, that as for conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the State they propoſe one generall publicke way: ſo for the eaſe of tender conſciences, and for avoyding of ſinne either in compelling of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip contrary to conſcience, or in reſtraint of conſciencious worſhip; they would be pleaſed to allow unto all men (that through difference of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not joyne with the publicke congregations) the free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed exerciſe of their conſciences in private congregations.</p>
            <p>And if they ſhould be pleaſed ſo to doe; it is but what is agreeable to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon equity and true Chriſtian liberty: It hath beene the wiſdome of all judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Patriots to frame ſuch laws and government as all peaceable well min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded people might delight to live under; binding from all things palpably vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious by the greateſt puniſhments, and propoſing of rewards and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to all publicke vertue: but in things wherein every man ought to be fully perſwaded in his particular minde of the lawfulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe thereof; there to leave every man to the guidance of his owne judgement; and where this rule is obſerved, there all things flouriſh, for thither will reſort all ſorts of ingenious free borne minds: ſuch Commonwealths abound with all things either neceſſary or delightfull, and which is the chiefe ſupport of all: ſuch a government aboundeth with wiſe men, and with the generall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the people: for where the government equally reſpecteth the good and peace of all ſorts of virtuous men, without reſpect of their different judgements in matters of Religion: there all ſorts of judgements cannot but love the government, and eſteem nothing too pretious to ſpend in defence thereof.</p>
            <p>Who can live where he hath not the freedome of his minde, and exerciſe of his conſcience? looke upon thoſe Governments that deny this liberty, and obſerve the envyings and repinings that are amongſt them, and how can it be otherwiſe, when as if a man advance in knowledge above what the State alloweth, he can no longer live freely, or without diſturbance exerciſe his conſcience? what follows then? why he takes his eſtate, and trade, and family, and removes where he may freely enjoy his minde, and exerciſe his conſcience: and as this hath been the ſad condition of this Nation to its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame loſſe divers wayes: ſo Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> would have it continued for ought by his writings can bee diſcovered; nor is he any whit troubled in ſpirit to ſee at this day of Jubile, and of Reformation unto all juſt liberty: thouſands of well-affected perſons at their wits end, not knowing where to ſet their foot, for want of encouragement in the cauſe of conſcience.</p>
            <p>I but, ſayes Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> our Covenant bindes us to maintaine an abſolute Eccleſiaſtick power in the Parliament: it bindes us to maintaine their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted rights, power, priviledges: but Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> muſt ever beare in minde, that what the people cannot entruſt that they cannot have; which will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all objections of that nature.</p>
            <p>As for our Brethren of Scotland: there is no doubt, but they are ſad obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of all the diſtempers and miſunderſtandings that are amongſt us, and would be moſt glad that the wiſdome of Parliament would miniſter a ſpeedy remedy; although therein they ſhould ſomewhat vary from their way of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159262:6"/>Church Government; as well knowing there can be no greater advantage given to our common Enemy, then the continuance of theſe our diviſions and diſaffections.</p>
            <p>And where Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> may ſuppoſe all liberty of this kinde, would tend to the encreaſing of erronious opinions, and diſturbance to the State; I beleeve he is miſtaken; for let any mans experience witneſſe whether freedome of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be not the readieſt way both to give and receive ſatisfaction in all things.</p>
            <p>And as for diſturbance to the State: admit any mans judgement be ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed, as to beleeve there is no ſinne; if this man now upon this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould take away another mans goods, or commit murder or adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the Law is open, and he is to be puniſhed as a malefactor, and ſo for all crimes that any mans judgement may miſlead him unto.</p>
            <p>And truly you are to conſider in reading his great Book (improperly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, Truth triumphing over falſhood) that he acknowledges them to bee but nocturnall lucubrations, diſtracted ſubitane collections; and if you truly weigh them you will finde them very light, and little better compacted then meere dreams, or ſuch fumes as men uſe to have betwixt ſleeping and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: and when you have viewed all thoſe many ſheets, conſider them as in one, and it will reſemble Saint <hi>Peters</hi> viſion, a mixt multitude of unclean te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies raked out of the ſerpentine dens of meer tyrannous Princes, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian and Machivillian Councells, erronious Parliaments, and bloudy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Councells and Convocations, which he hath produced, to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaders and controlers in theſe times of pure Reformation. Certainly if a man were not in a deep Lethargy, ſuch a maſſe of ſo groſſe excrements could not paſſe from him without offence to his owne noſtrill; if it be his caſe, hee that ſcracheth him moſt, and handles him moſt roughly, is his beſt friend, there being no other remedy; when he is recovered and broad awake hee will thanke his Phyſitian: in the meane time thus much is preſented to his admirers, to preſerve them from that malevolent infection, unto which his writings and reputation of former ſufferings might ſubject them unto; and this by one who is no more obliged to any Independent, Anabaptiſt, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, Separation, or Antinomian, then Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> himſelfe; but hath taken paines to know them ſomewhat better, and cannot but love them for their ſincere love to our dear Country, to the juſt liberties thereof, and to our juſt Parliamentary Government: moſt heartily wiſhing them their juſt deſires, and a peacefull life amongſt us: That they might be encouraged to joyne heart and hand with us, in proſecution of the common Enemies, of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon liberties, knowing no reaſon why I ſhould not love and aſſiſt every perſon that loves his Country unfeignedly, and endeavours to promote the good and freedome thereof, though of different judgement with me in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion; in which caſe I am not to judge or controle him, nor he me: and I heartily wiſh all true lovers of their Country were in this minde; and when they are ſo, then the miſeries of this Nation will ſoon be ended, and untill then, they will continue, as is too much to be feared: I could heartily wiſh that what is here written, might worke a good alteration in Mr. <hi>Pryn:</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:159262:6"/>but when I remember the ſtory, That a certain Lawyer came to our Saviour, tempting him; I fear it is in reſpect of himſelf, but waſhing of a Blackamoore: ſelf deniall, is too hard a leſſon for him; and if ſo, you ſhall have him in ſome bitter reply inſtantly; for though he cannot out-reaſon men, yet if he can but out-write his oppoſers, he claps his wings and crows <hi>victoria,</hi> that he hath ſilenced them all. Truly for writing much, I verily believe that he out-does any man in England, which is no commodity at all to a State or the Truth, and then conſidering what free liberty he hath to Print whatſoever he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, diſcreet men will conſider what a great advantage he hath therein, and will not deem it want of ability in his oppoſers, though they doe not ſee him preſently anſwered to their full ſatisfaction; and yet I am confident his great Booke will be ſuddenly anſwered throughly: but if Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> would deale upon equall tearmes, and uſe meanes that the Preſſe may be open for all Subjects, but for ſix moneths next comming free from the bonds of Licencers; if Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> be not ſo ſilenced, as that all his former and late books doe not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſell browne paper; let me be henceforward eſteemed as vaine a boaſter, as now I eſteem him: for his oppoſers, as in the juſtneſſe of this cauſe they cannot regard his ſpleene; ſo nothing would be more welcome to them then his love, and change of minde, whereof ſome doe not diſpaire: however, I end with his owne words, more juſtly applyed <hi>fiat juſtitia;</hi> better it is that he undergoe this my plaine dealing, then that either the Readers of his bookes ſhould be ſeduced, or ſo many innocent well-affected perſons be ſo groſſely abuſed by him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
